Hi and welcome back to another video
with Math Skills to ACE Chemistry.
We're gonna be going over how to
round sig figs, meaning that if
we are doing all these different
calculations or measurements and.
All this different mathematics.
When it comes to chemistry, we need to
make sure we are representing our values
with the correct amount of significance.
Meaning that if you're doing an
experiment, and let's say if you take
one measurement with a beaker, you take
another one with like a graduated cylinder
and so different piece of glassware, and
then you do another one with a $50,000
piece of chemical instrumentation.
Well, Some of those are pretty accurate.
One of them you're paying a lot of
money for, so, but if you use like a
beaker, let's say, to measure the amount
of liquid you put into the, into the
instrument in the beginning, well that
might not be, it might set off your
values possibly, or who knows, depending
on how you did the experiment, there's a
possibility that is not completely showing
the correct amount of significance.
So, we need to make sure that when
we do chemical calculations, We
are representing it by whatever
we shirked off the most, most on.
So if you were kind of lazy on one part
of it, well sadly, you gotta represent
all your numbers based on that value.
So let's take a look at it.
Let's try to see what this is all about.
So if I have the following example, so if
I have the following number, it's 26.542.
And if we wanted to kinda label all these
different numbers here, well remember just
kind of review our places of a decimal.
Usually this is what we're typically
rounding most of the time in
chemistry is the decimal place.
Where do you want to put it?
Well, if we're looking at these, sometimes
we are gonna be seeing different labels,
which maybe you remember from high school.
Maybe you don't, and that's okay too.
That's why we're going over it.
So these are the tenth place, the
hundredth place, the thousandth
place of that little TH just
tells you it's after the decimal.
So it's was the first, second,
or third position tells you what
you might have to round it to.
So if you're using a piece of, of
glassware that only goes to the hundredth
position, well then you need to round
it correctly and cut off numbers.
So what you're gonna be doing is
when you're rounding, you always
look to the digit on the right.
So let's say, for example, if I ask you
to round to the tenth position here.
So rounding right in here and
let's clean that up for a second.
So if I tell you right here, the
tenth spot is what we're gonna be
rounding, well, how would we do that?
Well, the whole idea when it comes to
rounding is you look to the digit on the
right, meaning that when we are doing
this, we want to stick a big underline
right under our five, and then we're gonna
be looking at the four value next door.
Now when we're doing that, what do you do?
Well, if the digit is zero
to four, you round down.
So meaning whatever's on the
right, you round down, meaning
you keep your five at what it is.
If the digit to the right is five
or nine, you're gonna round up.
So in this case, looking at
this, well, five was next to
four, meaning that we round down.
So when we do this, we
keep it at its number.
We don't round it up.
So in this case, what would it be?
Well, it's going to be 26.5 is going to
be our final number in this situation
because we had a four next to it.
You want the, the lower
value to represent that.
Now, if I take the same number and I
ask you, okay, why don't you try to
round to the nearest hundredth place?
Which is this second spot?
Well, same situation here.
We look over, we look one to the right,
we could see, well, it's zero to four.
Okay.
So that's telling you, all
right, we gotta round down again.
So how would we show that value?
Well, it would be 26.54.
Would be our number.
And this tells you how many
significant figures you have, right?
So we rounded it to show four sig
figs, which might be how many, is
a very common amount you need for
a lot of chemical calculations.
I asked you another example.
What if I asked you to
give you the other half?
If I asked you round it to the
10 or the the tens position, her.
So not tens, but the ones position.
Sorry.
And if you were to do that, well,
you're gonna once again look
over to the right and you see,
oh, this is greater than five.
So you're going to this case round up.
So what instead is that six is
going to go up and become a seven.
So that would make it 27.
So these are some of the
different ways you can round.
So, and you can see how many different
number of sig figs that you have.
In each of these rounding scenarios.
So this is why it's really important
'cause you want to represent however
many sig figs are appropriate
for your current situation.
So let's practice this
again to wrap up the video.
So round each number to the
underlined digit and determine
the number of significant figures.
Okay, so let's do it.
If we look at the first one.
We have four.
We're gonna look to the right
and we see that we have 3 32.452.
The five is is up there.
So five through nine you round up.
So in this case, what
are we going to have?
We're gonna make 332.5 is going to be
our number 'cause that four rounds up.
And if we want to count sig figs, this
would be a total of four non-zero digits.
We have four significant
figures in our calculation.
Now let's do the next one.
So we have eight thousand eight
hundred and two point fourteen, right.
However, we want to round that number.
So by doing this, we can look
over and we can see, all right,
well we can look to the right.
We see that as two, meaning
that it's from zero to four.
You round down.
In this case, are we going to show this?
Well, this one's a little weird 'cause.
If we round down, do we drop
things and get rid of it?
No.
We need to make sure we're still
showing the correct number of
placeholders in our calculation.
It still has to show the same
general size of the value.
So when we do this, we have 800
or 8,800 would be our value.
Notice that it still
shows that same value.
We don't drop the zero.
We don't just drop it as it is.
A common error that I see a lot of
students do is that in this case,
you might have wrote 880 and think
I'm good, but the thing is, think of
it in this light and you'll probably
will won't do this mistake again.
Let's think of this all in terms of money.
People never forget money.
Let's say someone owed you $8,800.
They're like, oh, I rounded
it and here's $880 because I
dropped that significant figure.
You would not be very
happy about that, right?
To get paid a 10th of what
you're supposed to get paid.
Right?
So you still wanna show the same
size of value that's supposed to be.
So that's the whole idea, right?
It shows what is the,
the right place or size.
So when we look at this, we only have.
Two significant figures because
in this case, there's no decimal.
So the trailing zeros are not significant.
So when we round it, it gets rid of
the decimal when you round it in the
middle of the big side of these numbers.
Okay, now the next one
I have 3000 or 35,402.
Same idea, right?
We have five and we wanna look over
and we're gonna be rounding down.
So we're gonna have 35.
Hundred is going to be our answer here.
We only have two significant
figures because the trailing
zeros are not significant.
The next one, oh, what the heck is that?
Well, this is scientific notation.
This is gonna be the next video.
So scientific notation
is a very easy way to.
Kind of minimize or to make
smaller lot really big numbers
or really, really small numbers.
But the cool thing about scientific
notation is the numbers that are
in front of that multiplication
symbol are the only numbers that
represent any significant digits.
So before rounding, just to kind
of let you know, there are four
sig figs currently in this number.
We don't count the times 10 to the fifth.
That's just telling you how much you're
moving a decimal when you wanna show
this in its numeric or standard form.
So if we wanna round it, we could leave
it in this form, which is awesome.
So you take that zero, you look
over at the seven and we see that,
okay, well it's gonna round up.
So in this case we'll have 1.31 and
we have our number sig figs there.
So this tells you you
have 1, 2, 3 sig figs.
And we can't forget to bring
down the times 10 to the fifth.
Now, this is scientific notation form.
What this tells you is eventually
what we're gonna go over in the
next video is how you can show
in standard form, all right?
This is how you can count
and round different examples.
So hopefully this helps with future
homework assignments and to help
you in your chemistry course.
It says, Dr.
Dan here, please hit the
like and subscribe button.
Hit comment below if you have any
questions or if you need help or have
any future videos you'd love to see.
All right.
Thank you so much and
I'll see you all soon.
Bye now.